# Ankur Singh

+1 (408) 941 - 5818 | ankur.singh01@sjsu.edu | ankur-singh.github.io

## Summary

With over 4+ years of experience specializing in the domains of Product Management, Deep Learning, Computer Vision, and Software Development. I am passionately curious in solving business problems by building products and services from the ground up. A lifelong learner, tinkerer and a team builder. In my recent stint, I built a phenomenal team of 6 members and deployed 4 ML services in production in just 10 months. Before that, I developed 5 full-fledged courses on topics around ML/DL and mentored over 600+ students.

## Skills

**Languages** Python, SQL, Shell Scripting, JAVA (elementary proficiency)

**Databases** Postgres, SQLite3, MongoDB, Redis

**Web Development** Flask, FastAPI, Rest APIs, Web scraping

**Software Development** CI/CD, Git, Docker, Pytest, Python Packaging

**ML/DL Frameworks,** Scikit-Learn, Pytorch, Pandas, Keras, Fastai, Pytorch Lightning, YOLOv5, YOLOR, U2net, Timm,

**Libraries & Git repos** Torchvision, Segmentation Models Pytorch (SMP), Hugging Face, MMOCR, MMDetect,

PaddleOCR, XGboost, LightGBM, Catboost, Categorical Encoding, Spacy, NLTK.

**Deep Learning CV:** Classification, Regression, Object Detection, Segmentation, Keypoint detection. **Problems NLP:** Classification, Text Generation, NER. POS tagging, Neural Machine translation (

**NLP:** Classification, Text Generation, NER, POS tagging, Neural Machine translation (NMT). **Others:** OCR, Face Detection, Recognition, and Matching; Recommendation System, Similarity Search, Unsupervised Learning, GANs, Tabular Data, Multi-Label, Multimodal Arch.

# Work Experience

## San Jose State University

San Jose, CA

GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Sept. 2017 - present

Building an Edge AI platform to deploy and manage ML/DL models at scale on Edge devices for real-time inference.

Zoop.One Pune, India

TEAM LEAD - MACHINE LEARNING

Sept. 2021 - Jul. 2022

As a Founding Member of the ML team, built a phenomenal team of 6 ML engineers and led a large effort to scale up the use of ML across the company. I improved the state of MLOps (from level-0 to level-1) by setting up annotation tools, model registry, monitoring, automating model training, and establishing other best practices.

### OCR Service

- Developed a OCR service to extract relevant information from Identity Cards like PAN, Aadhaar, Driving License & Passport. It served as the backend for multiple Sign-up, Verification & enrollment journeys in several products.
- The service had more than 7 deep learning models to detect and extract cards, correct card orientation, enhance the image, identify card type, layout analysis, and OCR to extract textual information.
- Our service was almost 4 to 6 times faster than other players in the market and was much more accurate. Additionally, we provide support for multi-line names & addresses that no other player was offering.

#### Document Scanner Service

- This service enabled numerous front-end services to extract ID cards and documents from any given image.
- Tried several different approaches for ID card / document extraction like edge detection using conventional CV, object detection, segmentation, keypoint regression & heatmap regression.
- Developed Heatmap Regression based document extractor to facilitate auto-cropping in any ID card or Document.
- Built a service around the above model and deployed it so that it can be easily consumed by the front-end teams.
- Also, compressed and exported the model to TFLite (4.4 MB) for edge deployment.

#### · Liveliness Service

- This service provided features like face detection, face recognition, face matching, and other face details like age, gender, race, etc. Furthermore, it also had modules to check for eyeglasses, face mask, liveliness and spoof detection.
- Developed a config driven backend, allowing front-end teams to dynamically turn on/off any module on per request basis. There was also an option to save configurations.
- Low latency (~150 ms for liveliness & spoof detection) allowed us to do real-time inference on video feeds. While other competitors were using active liveliness techniques, we used passive liveliness, with very high accuracy.

#### Other Roles & Responsibilities

- Identify areas of improvement in existing services and investigate new technologies like MLflow model registry, CVAT, Label Studio, Weights & Bias, FiftyOne, torch serve, KF serve, Ray Serve, etc.
- Regularly conducted training sessions to help new and junior team members.
- Developed frameworks to train classification, regression, object detection & segmentation models. Frameworks also had support for preparing & validating data, experiment tracking, model validation, exporting models, and publishing models to MLflow model registry. Furthermore, frameworks can be used either as scripts or CLI or python code.

AiAdventures LLP

CO-FOUNDER & CEO

Pune, India

Aug. 2018 - Sept. 2021

We provided AI/ML solutions to businesses, and trained people in Data Science & Machine Learning.

- **Developed full-fledged courses** for Python, Data Science, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, & Computer Vision. Each course had at least 9 hrs of content in the form of Jupyter notebooks, assignments, quizzes, questionnaires, & projects.
- Built the tech-stack required for generation, deployment & distribution of all courses.
- Helped 600+ students get started with python & Data science.
- Conducted 25+ college and corporate workshops on SOTA Machine Learning and Deep Learning systems.
- Wrote 20+ blogs on topics related to Python, Data Science, ML, DL, databases, etc.
- Managing and developing client projects.

# **Extracurricular Projects**

- Built a python package called "colab-everything" which lets you run web-apps on any jupyter notebook like environment. The library has over 22K+ downloads.
- Won Grand Prize in "Al for Social Good" hackathon at Intel Innovation 2022.
- Have contributed to Fastai, MLflow, LazyPredict, Pytorch Lighting, Category Encoding, YOLOv5, etc.
- Build **Bank Cheque service** that allows one to extract bank and account details from canceled cheques.
- Used ULMfit to perform Aspect Based Sentiment Analysis (for Hindi text) for restaurant & product reviews (published by IIT Patna). Achieved SOTA results in both sentiment & aspect classification tasks. ULMfit was trained on Hindi text scraped from wikipedia. Technologies: BeautifulSoup, NLTK, Spacy, Fastai, Pytorch, XML, SemEval
- Trained YOLO & Faster-RCNN detection models to detect jewelries in images. Used **unsupervised learning** (triplet & contrastive loss) to find similar images in the database. The application was exposed as Rest APIs. **Technologies:** Pytorch, FAISS, Flask, Rest-API, OpenCV, React, MongoDB, Docker

# **Kaggle Competitions**

#### **Shopee-Price Match Guarantee**

Bronze Medal (207th / 2426)

- Task was to identify similar products using product image, title, description, and phash.
- It was a similarity search problem with new unseen products in the test set.
- Used unsupervised and self supervised learning techniques (like SIMCLR, SWAV, ARCFace loss), and **multi-modal model** to extract product features, followed by KNN (FAISS & Rapis) & ranking to find similar products.

Global Wheat Detection Bronze Medal (191st / 2245)

- Task was to detect wheat heads from field images across the globe.
- It was an Object detection problem with extremely noisy data and numerous wrong labels.
- Used YOLOv5, EfficientDet-B5, pseudo labeling, knowledge distillation, mosaic augmentation, Test Time Augmentation (TTA).

Mechanisms of Action

Bronze Medal (318th / 4373)

- Task was to measure the effect of drugs on genes and cells.
- It was a **multi-label** classification problem with 897 input features and 207 output labels.
- Used an ensemble of LightGBM, Tabnet and Custom Pytorch models.

## **Education**

## San Jose State University (SJSU)

San Jose, California

MASTERS IN SOFTWARE ENGINEERING

Aug. 2022 - May 2024

• Major Area of Specialization in **Data Science**.

## College of Engineering, Pune (COEP)

Pune, India

BACHELOR OF TECHNOLOGY IN INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY

Aug. 2014 - May 2018

• Cumulative Grade Point Average: 7.67/10